[About the days he was making an independent film]
There was an event called DAICON 3, the 20th Japan SF Convention.
I got the offer for the opening animation.
Powered suits and stuff like that would be in the animation, so they asked me to try.
I wasn't so interested in it, but Yamaga was very enthusiastic and wanted to do it.
No one knew about cel animation at the time.
There were only two staff members who had seen cels for cel animation before.
[Anno was in charge of the mecha, and Takao Akai was in charge of the original character drawing.]
I was drawing with Akai under such circumstances.
We managed to finish the animation and it was delivered on the day of the convention.
Mr. Miyatake and Mr. Kawamori of Studio Nue were at the convention by the way.
At the time, I was working on a tokusatsu film, so I couldn't spend a lot of time on the opening animation.
[In charge of designing mecha and monsters]
Only Yamaga went there.
Next year there was a science fiction convention called DAICON 4, and I was supposed to make an opening animation for it.
To do it with the same way we had before would have been bad, since no one knew how to do it.
So I decided to study the professional method.
How was it that professionals make animation?
It was worth going to study that.
For that reason, I worked on the Macross TV series when the special effects work calmed down.
I was working under Mr. Itano,
[In charge of starring, directing, and design]
I was so surprised to see how sloppy professional animator's work was.
I was studying by observation at that time, I wondered how they were making animations.
Then Mr. Itano showed up and piled up the cuts. He said, "You can choose any of these cut bags and then retouch it.".
That's why I did drawing.
So I don't have any experiences in video. I still work with messy lines.
And then I've been assigned to the mecha group.
I was working under Mr. Itano on the Macross TV series for 3 months.
But I needed to make an opening animation for DAICON 4, so I stopped it halfway.
I went back to Osaka and made the opening animation for DAICON 4 by making use of that sloppy professional experience.
Amazing. So that's why the world burned.
Her Majesty Kushana. Banzai! Banzai!
Burn them! What's the matter with you, monster? Can't you fire at once?
I had a different plan at first. Kushana wasn't coming by a tank, but walking beside the Giant God Warrior.
They were walking along, while the pieces of melted skin were dropping in front of Kushana.
It also had a scene of the Giant God Warrior battling against Ohmus.
That last shot of the Giant God Warrior wasn't so underwhelming, it's like he turns his face to the sky like this and shoots.
And he collapsed in a standing pose.
However we both worked too slowly
I mean, both the storyboard by Miyazaki and my key frames got finished too late.
The scale was gradually reduced, and in the end it became a film like it is now.
Work properly buddy!
Did it move forward?
Come out!
Anno, he is the most reliable person among the staff I know.
The reason for this is that he is a strange person. There are many things he can't do.
There are so many things he can't do, but in exchange what he can do is perfect and beautiful.
So I ask him what he can do. I don't ask him what he can't do.
He does the perfect job when you ask him to do what he can. So, I can say he is a truly reliable person.
Well, metaphorically speaking, Anno-kun is like a nuclear weapon.
If you use it incorrectly, radioactivity will contaminate your base as well.
However, if you use it well in the place where you use it, the war will end in one shot.
He is like a god who brings together the expanding fronts of animation and brings a wonderful end of the war with a single light.
[Depiction of mecha for Honneamise]
I try to put value in the first impression that I received.
Whether it's from a film or reality, airplanes are like this, smoke is like this, rockets are like this.
I tried to put those first impressions on the film as they are.
So it's not that so-called animation symbolic deformation,
But a deformation that values the real thing more.
I avoided making it more powerful by speeding it up. I also avoided manga-like images.
At any rate, I wanted to make it as close to the real thing as possible.
That's why I went to the USA and saw the shuttle launch.
I also joined the boot camp for new recruits conducted by the JSDF,
to see and touch real tanks and planes.
Only the depiction of the war, as you know I can't go to see the war.
For the image of the scene of the war, I refer to the actual literature books,
the texts of the war memorials, and the actual recording films.